Canadian Bulletin of Medical History
Volume 34, Issue 2, Fall 2017, Pages 297-326
https://doi.org/10.3138/cbmh.190-21122016
© Canadian Society for the History of Medicine / Société canadienne d'histoire de la médecine

AMS Paterson Lecture–Conférence AMS Paterson 2016

Vaccines, Pesticides, and Narratives of Exposure and Evidence

Elena Conis

Graduate School of Journalism, University of California, Berkeley

Abstract

This essay considers the cultural work performed by two public health narratives — the DDT narrative and the vaccine narrative — as they appeared in popular and professional discourse concerning two recent media events: controversy over an antivaccination film, and the emergence of a Zika global public health emergency. Like all narratives in the history of medicine, the stories historians and others tell about DDT and about vaccines organize a shared past to explain the present. They also point to a hoped-for future. The DDT and vaccine narratives share several themes: public health, expertise, evidence, exposure, and power. Their inclusions and exclusions, however, convey distinct messages about these themes, particularly regarding the right conduct of health citizens in the pursuit of public health. These narratives are analyzed to compare their agendas, and to propose a case study of how historical work can shed light on contemporary public health norms, practice, and challenges.

Résumé

Cet essai examine le travail culturel effectué par deux récits de santé publique — le récit du DDT et le récit du vaccin — tels qu'ils apparaissent dans le discours populaire et professionnel concernant deux événements médiatiques récents: la controverse sur un film anti-vaccination et l'émergence du Zika comme une urgence de santé publique mondiale. Comme tous les récits en histoire de la médecine, les histoires racontées par les historiens et d'autres intervenants au sujet du DDT et des vaccins organisent un passé partagé pour expliquer le présent et indiquer une direction pour l'avenir. Le DDT et les récits sur les vaccins partagent plusieurs thèmes: la santé publique, l'expertise, la preuve, l'exposition et le pouvoir. Leurs inclusions et exclusions véhiculent cependant des messages assez distincts sur ces thèmes et, par conséquent, sur la bonne conduite et la participation citoyenne favorisant la santé publique. Ces récits sont analysés afin de comparer leurs agendas et de proposer une étude de cas sur la façon dont le travail historique peut éclairer les normes, la pratique et les défis actuels de la santé publique.

Keywords

DDT
exposure
vaccines and antivaccination movements
Zika outbreaks
global health
public health and citizenship
health journalism
public health narratives and historiography

Mots-clés

exposition
DDT
vaccins et mouvements anti-vaccination
éclosions de Zika
santé mondiale
santé publique et citoyenneté
journalisme sur la santé
récit et historiographie sur la santé publique

Originally submitted 22 November 2016; accepted 9 January 2017.

Introduction

Two seemingly unrelated news stories took wing in 2016. One concerned the Zika virus and its spread across the Americas. The other concerned the film Vaxxed: From Cover-Up to Catastrophe and its spread across the United States. Each of these stories featured a “character” – DDT in the Zika story, vaccines in the Vaxxed story – familiar to those who have followed the West's recent public health debates. Vaccines and DDT are central to Western (and particularly American) public health's sense of identity as a profession, as they stand at the centre of stories, or narratives, about modern public health's capacity to vanquish disease and protect human life to an unprecedented extent – but not uncontroversially so. According to what might be called the grand narratives about vaccines and DDT, vaccines are powerfully lifesaving, but certain people avoid them for (usually) anti-scientific reasons; DDT was once an intensely popular chemical, integral to modern advances in public health and agriculture, but was abandoned in the West following the advent of new environmentalism. Neither of these narratives is fixed; nor is either one capable of containing the numerous sub-narratives about vaccines and DDT specific to particular times and spaces. The narratives that circulated in 2016 – which are the main subject of this essay – concern modern explanations as to why vaccines and DDT are not more widely used. The vaccine narrative maintains that vaccine-hesitant individuals have misguidedly followed a vaccination detractor, the director of Vaxxed, who produced illegitimate evidence about the risks of vaccines. The DDT narrative maintains that the balance of evidence on the pesticide's risks indicates that its use to protect human health ought to be highly constrained – even in the face of a threat such as Zika.

Both narratives thus ostensibly communicate the need to balance risks and benefits in the pursuit of public health. But they also concern whether chemical exposures matter in the pursuit of public health, when evidence is actionable in pursuit of the same, and who has the power to decide. The narratives' respective structures, moreover, convey fairly distinct messages about the themes of exposure, evidence, and expertise. The moral of the DDT story is to worry about still-contested exposures, question scientific evidence, and listen to renegade scientific voices; the moral of the vaccine narrative is that chemical exposures matter less than infectious threats, that scientific evidence need not be questioned, and that scientific consensus is more dependable than individual scientists with unorthodox views. In the vaccine narrative, scientific experts can be trusted because they don't make mistakes (and are sanctioned when they do); in the DDT narrative, scientific experts can be trusted because they learn from their past mistakes (and are magnanimous enough to admit when they do). News stories about Zika and Vaxxed provided occasion for particular forms of these two narratives to circulate in the same historical moment in 2016.[1] The narratives did not interact with each other directly, but their occupation of the same discursive space provides an opportunity to juxtapose the public health morals and values embedded in each one and to consider the implications of their contradictions.

These cultural narratives are evident throughout media coverage of the issues of vaccination and prevention of insect-borne disease, but this essay is not a media critique. I accept the idea from literary theory that narratives are works distinguished by the presence of story and storytellers, but I do not assume that journalists are the sole authors of these narratives.[2] Instead, I adopt the idea put forth by Charles Briggs and Daniel Hallin, in their work on bio-mediatization, that health knowledge is co-produced by an array of actors: reporters, medical and public health professionals, historians, other academics, representatives of industry and government, political and other public figures, and the public itself.[3] The vaccine and DDT narratives are evident in media coverage – but also in scientific journals, grand rounds, popular and scholarly books, textbooks, films, and more. What unifies these narratives is not their presence in the news media but, rather, their widespread circulation in narrative form – the fact that they are, to borrow an articulation from Jouni-Matti Kuukkanen, cognitive structures that connect statements and other material evidence in a logic intended to interpret and make meaning of the past.[4]

The idea that narrative co-producers select evidence from a messy past and organize it into a structure that gives meaning to that past is, admittedly, a contested view of narrative.[5] My aim in this essay is not to weigh in on narrative theory but to draw upon the philosophy of history that has engaged with narrative to consider how public health narratives, which are at least in part both products and objects of historical inquiry, may work at cross purposes in a manner that undermines public health goals encoded in state statutes and regulations. I have chosen to consider these structures narratives – as opposed to myths, or framed presentations of ideas – because they are teleological. Narrative structure assigns a beginning, a middle, and an end to past events; in scientific narratives, these time points give events, episodes, and individuals specific significance. Beginnings may assign priority and power by, for example, attributing credit for discoveries, theories, or approaches; endings can signal consensus about the state of the relevant evidence and its acceptance or rejection by a scientific majority or elite. In the vaccine and DDT narratives described below in greater detail, for example, vaccine and DDT doubts begin with single individuals and end when scientific evidence is accepted as validating or invalidating those doubts.

But this, of course, is only part of the story of vaccines and DDT. As historian William Cronon writes, narratives are constructed with “a rhetorical razor that defines included and excluded, relevant and irrelevant, empowered and disempowered”;[6] narratives, he adds, “cannot avoid a covert exercise of power,” because they sanction certain voices and views while silencing others.[7] The vaccine and DDT narratives are as noteworthy for the past episodes and voices they include as for those they exclude. And if narratives exert power by sanctioning some voices and silencing others, they give shape to and uphold hegemonic identities in the same way. Both narratives work to buttress an identity based on modern, middle-class, scientific values; poverty, for example, is missing from the vaccine narrative, occupational health from the DDT narrative, and religious and philosophical beliefs from both. This essay sets contemporaneous versions of these narratives not just in juxtaposition but in historical context, with attention to their inclusions and exclusions, to show how their content and structure provide clues to their respective messages, agendas, and power.

The Vaccine Narrative

A familiar cultural narrative concerning vaccines posits that the widespread vaccination of children is one of the greatest achievements of modern public health, responsible for preventing deaths and disability due to a long list of infectious diseases, including smallpox, polio, diphtheria, and measles.[8] Throughout the history of vaccination, the narrative maintains, most citizens have willingly accepted vaccination, though some groups have opposed it for a variety of reasons, including religious beliefs, health concerns, or ideological objections. A recent development in this narrative concerns a very specific reason for opposing vaccines: belief in a discredited scientific theory. The story of this belief is the vaccine narrative considered here.

This iteration of the vaccine narrative goes like this: in 1998, the medical journal The Lancet published a study by British gastroenterologist Andrew Wakefield purporting to have found a possible mechanistic link between the measles–mumps–rubella (MMR) vaccine and the development of autism in children.[9] That study, according to the narrative, kindled parental fears about vaccines and led parents to refuse vaccines for their children, which resulted in outbreaks of vaccine-preventable diseases such as measles and pertussis. As vaccine refusals accelerated, Wakefield was found guilty of scientific misconduct and stripped of his medical license, and in 2011 The Lancet retracted his study. Despite these developments, parents still believed in the link between vaccines and autism, and their vaccine fears continued to drive disease outbreaks.[10]

This turn-of-the-twenty-first-century vaccine narrative fits within larger historical narratives about vaccination that highlight post–World War II vaccination acceptance and enthusiasm and the recent emergence of “anti-vaccinationism” as a reprise of Progressive Era vaccination opposition. I use this specific vaccine narrative here because it fits neatly within larger historical vaccine narratives and because it has been cited repeatedly in cultural stories about vaccines for the better part of the last decade. When a 2015 US measles outbreak was traced to California's Disneyland, Forbes blamed it on parents who espoused anti-vaccinationism because of Wakefield's theory.[11] Newsweek reported similarly when measles broke out in Berlin in that same year.[12] After Wakefield published his study, reported National Geographic, “vaccination rates dropped in Britain and Western Europe, and [his] theory lived on in Internet chat rooms and among believers of the anti-vax movement.”[13] The theory was behind rising rates of rising rates of measles in England and Wales in 2009 and a 2008 outbreak of the disease in San Diego, reported the Los Angeles Times.[14] Wakefield's study had been debunked, retracted, and disproven countless times by other researchers, and yet still parents weren't vaccinating their children, according to the New York Times.[15]

The vaccine narrative has been invoked repeatedly during outbreaks of vaccine-preventable infections, but in early 2016, it surfaced in a different context: a controversy over the release of Vaxxed, a documentary directed by Wakefield. The film – which focuses on the actions of a CDC whistleblower named William Thompson – argues that the link between vaccines and autism has been kept hidden by unethical practices among CDC scientists and the agency's close ties to the pharmaceutical industry. Vaxxed was scheduled to make its debut with a screening at the internationally renowned Tribeca Film Festival, co-founded by actor Robert De Niro, but when news of its inclusion was released in late March, it immediately sparked a firestorm of outrage on social and mainstream media.

News outlets called Wakefield a “quack,” the film's premise “highly questionable,” and the film itself something that “could put kids' lives in danger,” and quoted doctors and other experts stating the same.[16] De Niro defended the decision to include the documentary, saying the issue was “deeply personal” – but before the month was through, the festival pulled the film.[17] Media reports on the documentary almost universally invoked the vaccine narrative. “We can trace the current fad for not vaccinating babies and children straight back to the former doctor, and – surprise! – he's still going,” reported New York Magazine.[18] “Ever since the February 1998 publication of the now-retracted paper that set this eternal train in motion … health has been threatened, lives have been lost,” reported Forbes.[19] Such invocations conveyed the message that Wakefield lacked scientific credibility; that vaccine fears were universally attributable to Wakefield, and therefore scientifically unfounded; that giving credence to Wakefield posed a direct threat to human life, and that there was no room for debate. “There are not two sides to every story,” concluded a reporter for Salon.[20]

Historians, too, rarely accept that there are two sides to every story – although the discipline's default position is that there are usually more than two. And indeed, countless stories were ignored in this narrative's construction. The narrative makes no mention of other factors driving vaccine-preventable disease outbreaks, such as under-vaccination among the poor and uninsured, waning vaccine-induced immunity, and evolving pathogens. It also fails to acknowledge that concerns about the relationship between vaccines and autism considerably antedate Wakefield's study; they can be traced to at least the early 1980s, when parents who described themselves as vaccine safety advocates demanded reduction of the brain-damage risk associated with the pertussis component of the combined diphtheria–pertussis–tetanus vaccine.[21] The persistence of worries about vaccine-induced developmental delays in children led to autism worries that persisted from the 1980s into the 1990s and that accumulated as autism rates rose alongside the number of vaccines required for children in the 1990s and 2000s. From this perspective, Wakefield and his colleagues undertook their study in response to worries about a potential vaccine–autism link well before they could ever have been considered a cause of such worries.[22]

Placing the responsibility for vaccine rejection on Wakefield's shoulders also ignores the diverse concerns vaccine sceptics voiced from the 1970s into the 2000s, as the vaccine schedule for children grew lengthier and more complicated. Historically, anti-vaccinationists who opposed vaccines for the risks they carried cited health consequences associated with the biological components or contaminants of vaccines, including the microbial causes of erysipelas, syphilis, and tetanus. Beginning in the 1970s – when there were more vaccines than ever for children, when laws requiring them became the default approach to ensuring a widely vaccinated public, and when enforcement of such laws was carried out to an extent never before seen outside of epidemic contexts – the focus of risk-based vaccine worries broadened. The vaccine safety movement that organized in response to revelations about the risks of pertussis vaccination in the 1980s pointed to biological “impurities” in the vaccine. But some critics also began scrutinizing the chemical components of vaccines, including ingredients such as formaldehyde, glycerin, thimerosal, and aluminum.[23]

This scrutiny was a response to numerous factors, including the patient's rights movement's focus on informed consent; the women's health movement's emphasis on self-education; and an anti-medicalization movement that led some to question the new push for vaccination against infections, such as measles and mumps, long considered a normal part of childhood. This scrutiny also made sense at a time when chemical exposures associated with nearly every aspect of life, from house paint to physician-prescribed drugs, had been identified as causes of long-term and cross-generational health effects, including learning disabilities and cancer.[24] The fact that vaccines were increasingly understood as sources of chemical exposure in the last decades of the twentieth century led, not unreasonably, to questions about the connection between vaccination and neurological disorders and developmental disabilities – including autism – in addition to allergies, asthma, and immune conditions. The vaccine narrative excises all of these and, as a consequence, denies the claim that vaccines are an exposure of public health concern.

Pinpointing the origins of contemporary vaccine worries to Wakefield's 1998 study further renders exposure worries inviable because it erases an important, concurrent exposure-related episode: the policy decision to remove the mercury-based preservative thimerosal from vaccines for children. At the beginning of the 1990s, the US Congress asked the Environmental Protection Agency to study the health and environmental consequences of mercury emissions, and, in an amendment to the Food and Drug Administration Modernization Act of 1997, asked the FDA to evaluate the mercury in drugs and biologics. These moves were a response to recent research revealing potentially harmful mercury levels in the atmosphere, the food supply, and bodies. The FDA's investigation led to a 1999 statement in which the Public Health Service and the American Academy of Pediatrics asked manufacturers to eliminate or reduce “the mercury content of their vaccines,” citing the expanded number of vaccines added to the schedule recommended for children as cause for concern. Public health experts were divided on the decision, but the statement, and the vaccine reformulations that followed, gave credence to the notion that vaccine ingredients were exposures of consequence. The thimerosal episode received significant media attention; Wakefield's study, released the previous year, received little to none in the United States (although a bit more in the United Kingdom).[25] And yet, in the contemporary vaccine narrative, Wakefield takes the blame for a trend and a set of worries well entrenched before his work was published – a narrative construction that conveys the idea that vaccine exposures don't matter and never did.

The vaccine narrative omits two more significant histories of vaccination scepticism at the turn of the twenty-first century: the development of vaccine doubts among adults concerned for their own health, not that of their children, and the influence of changing attitudes toward drug manufacturers on lay attitudes toward vaccines. Objection to new vaccination policies in the 1990s and 2000s broke out among health care workers required to receive the hepatitis B vaccine (and, later, the flu vaccine) and members of the military required to receive the anthrax and smallpox vaccines.[26] As the most expensive vaccine ever brought to market, the hepatitis B vaccine, introduced in the late 1980s, sparked worries about the costs of vaccines, which, in the United States, president Bill Clinton helped cultivate by sharply criticizing drug manufacturers as a “special interest” as he pressed for a universal vaccine purchase program for the country in the 1990s.[27] The backlash against “Big Pharma” that built from the late 1990s into the early 2000s further conditioned consumers to see vaccines as pricey, possibly unnecessary commodities, and expert assurances of vaccine safety as compromised by close associations among drug developers, regulators, and policy makers and by the rush to bring profitable new drugs to market. These factors (among others) led to robust public rejection of the new human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine introduced in 2006, as well as of the US state laws introduced to require it for young girls. This episode, too, is a critical element of the story of popular vaccine hesitancy at the turn of the millennium, but it is entirely left out of the vaccine narrative starring Wakefield.

There are practical reasons why the stripped-down vaccine narrative exists, including the economy of communication necessitated by journalism, academic writing, and policy discussions. Moreover, Wakefield, a well-spoken and charismatic individual, acts in ways that demand attention – directing a film on vaccine risks included in the Tribeca festival being a case in point. But the narrative appears in discourse well outside of events directly involving him, including that concerning the 2015 Disneyland measles outbreak. It is possible to imagine that the contemporary vaccine narrative could just as easily trace today's vaccine hesitancy and rejection to the statement on thimerosal released in 1999, especially as not all thimerosal has been removed from all vaccines. But it doesn't, because such a narrative simply wouldn't further the same agenda as the one starring Wakefield.

Juxtapose the narrative's inclusions with its exclusions, and its agenda becomes apparent. The vaccine narrative endorses the vaccination status quo – the enforced vaccination of children against a growing list of increasingly diverse infections – by shutting out unanswerable questions and unresolvable issues. It affirms that vaccination is strictly a medical matter; that it works when parents trust in experts; and that it is without risk or consequence – that there are no issues related to vaccination worthy of discussion beyond the matter raised by Wakefield and subsequently settled by a consensus of scientists. It is no accident that the star is Wakefield, a former physician, that the object is a single vaccine (MMR) and a single feared condition (autism), that truth comes in the form of scientific consensus, and that supporting roles are played by parents who purportedly believe in a disproven scientific theory.

By homing in on the idea that vaccine avoidance is a consequence of autism fears, the narrative asserts that there are no other reasons that people fear or resist vaccines. It offers no place for a long and complicated list of lay medical questions related to vaccination – not just about the connection between vaccination and developmental and neurological conditions beyond autism, or between vaccination and allergies or asthma, but about the health of the human immune system, both today and in future generations. The roots of vaccination resistance are not merely medical in nature, as lawmakers, health experts, and historians have long known. Mark Largent has cogently captured the diversity of parental vaccine questions and concerns in the early twenty-first century: the fear that children receive “too many” vaccines “too soon”; that the schedule of vaccines for children exceeds the unknown capacity of young immune systems to handle immunological tinkering; that all vaccines are treated as equally urgent despite dramatic differences among the infections they prevent; that vaccination is increasingly “tickling” the line between medical therapy and medical “enhancement”; and that humankind has yet to resolve practical and philosophical questions about the ultimate goal of expanding immunization, if not the complete elimination of all infectious disease.[28] The vaccine narrative discredits all of these issues – and more.

The narrative's focus on a single vaccine makes questions about the length of the vaccine schedule a non-issue. Its treatment of this single vaccine as representative presents all vaccines as equivalently safe and urgent. Its attention to a single and unsupported vaccine risk dismisses the existence of other risks, whether theoretical or real. By defining vaccine safety as something that can be proved within a few years or decades, the narrative excises concerns about how vaccination is reshaping human bodies from one generation to the next. And its selection of a vaccination question settled through epidemiological methods affirms vaccination as the exclusive domain of public health and medical experts, leaving no room for philosophical or ideological debate. The narrative's delegitimizing of philosophical or subjective questions makes possible the elimination of philosophical exemptions to vaccination mandates in US states, such as that signed into law in California following the outbreak of measles traced to Disneyland in 2015.[29]

This narrative, like all narratives, makes sense for its moment and its medium and carries a sanctioned set of morals: that public health is a top-down activity, its experts dependable and trustworthy, its technologies safe, effective, and to be used by an unquestioning public. It's a set of morals, in short, that function in many ways in opposition to the moral of the contemporaneous narrative concerning DDT.

The DDT Narrative

DDT has often been proclaimed one of the most important public health discoveries of the twentieth century, a distinction that puts stories about the chemical on par with vaccine narratives for their cultural prominence and influence. The organochlorine compound dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane, first synthesized in the late nineteenth century, was discovered to be a potent insect killer in the late 1930s. Its insecticidal properties were uncovered by a scientist at the Swiss chemical manufacturer Geigy, but as the chemical's story acquired shape and meaning in North America, particularly in the United States, its Swiss origins were often downplayed in favour of the drama that subsequently played out in the United States and on the global stage.[30]

The simple DDT narrative goes like this: the discovery of DDT, the least toxic and most powerful insect killer of its time, helped the Allies win World War II by clearing battlegrounds of disease-carrying insects that threatened Allied troops. During and after the war, DDT was dubbed a miracle, likened to the atomic bomb, and hailed a hero of the war effort. After the war, the Geigy chemist was awarded a Nobel Prize and postwar Americans enthusiastically welcomed DDT into their homes and neighbourhoods, dousing themselves and their environment with the chemical without question – until Rachel Carson published her 1962 critique of pesticides, Silent Spring. This book, which helped inspire the environmental movement, turned public sentiment so firmly against the insecticide that the United States ultimately banned it in 1972.

The American story of DDT often ends there, but the chemical's history includes another dimension often cited in narratives that emphasize its global public health and medical importance. In this story, DDT deserves special recognition for eliminating malaria from the United States and for its central role in a global, World Health Organization (WHO)–led malaria eradication campaign launched in the 1950s. The US DDT ban, according to this narrative, brought the campaign to a halt, and malaria rebounded in the decades that followed. In the 1990s, with malaria proving intractable in the world's poorest regions, including much of sub-Saharan Africa, health experts began to debate whether it was time to “bring back” DDT. When more than 90 nations signed the Stockholm Convention calling for a global ban on persistent organic pollutants in 2004, they made an exception for DDT in areas with few other good resources for combating the disease, and pledged to continue to evaluate the right time and place for DDT – a project that continues to this day.[31]

The DDT narrative has a broader reach than the vaccine narrative, largely because it is not confined to public health. For this reason, it has become a legible reference point in college lectures, textbooks, trade books, documentaries, and more on war, the rise of a global superpower, Western consumerism, industrial agriculture, the environment, and the social movements to protect it. The DDT narrative appears in media reporting, too, waxing and waning with debates about the regulatory reach of the state or perceived health or environmental threats. As West Nile virus spread across North America in the early 2000s, for example, op-eds and pundits reminisced about DDT and recounted its story in conversations about whether it was time for the pesticide's return.[32] When bedbug infestations broke out in major metropolitan areas a few years after that, DDT's story was trotted out again as talking heads battled over whether the comeback could be blamed on the global north's DDT ban.[33] Early in 2016, DDT's story began to recirculate once more, this time in reporting on the outbreak of the mosquito-borne Zika virus.

Zika, a so-called emerging infection, first appeared in the Americas in 2015. In March of that year it cropped up in Brazil, and seven months later it had spread so quickly that the country “ceased counting cases.”[34] The virus had been suspected of causing microcephaly in past outbreaks; a new cluster in Brazil seemed to confirm the link.[35] Zika is carried by Aedes aegypti, which news reports dubbed “a particularly wily foe” and “the cockroach” of mosquitoes, with a range from the United States to Argentina.[36] With the WHO announcing that Zika was “spreading explosively” and Brazil scheduled to host the 2016 Summer Olympic Games, public health officials across the Americas offered guidance on curbing Zika's damage: delay pregnancy, use repellent and clothing to guard against bites, and take measures to eliminate the mosquito.[37] In early 2016, the New York Times reported that with “standard” anti-mosquito methods proving insufficient against Zika, DDT was “being mentioned a bit” by “some experts” who believed it still had a place in controlling disease.[38]

Throughout the first half of 2016, DDT cropped up repeatedly in reporting and popular discourse on Zika. Some reports summed up DDT's entire life story, from wartime discovery to 1970s ban to turn-of-the-millennium reconsideration. Others simply referenced one or another aspect of DDT's past, typically to make points relevant to the present. In the many versions of DDT's story that were repeated in this context, the pesticide was a technology that determined the victors in war and whose excellence was a signifier of US (and Western) supremacy. DDT “played a crucial role in helping Allied forces,” reported Time that winter.[39] The Los Angeles Times recounted how, when 500 American soldiers a day began succumbing to dengue fever during the 1944 US invasion of Saipan, their commanders “blasted” a 25-square-mile area (almost 65 km^2) with kerosene and DDT. The outcome: “Aegypti lost, and then so did the Japanese.”[40] Press accounts told of how DDT fell out of favour less than a generation later, when a “movement” inspired by Silent Spring was no longer willing to withstand the pesticide's damage to the environment, “especially bird populations.”[41] US hegemony is no less important to this turn in the narrative, as the country's decision prompted other nations to “follow suit” and “join the U.S.” in implementing bans of their own. This narrative inclusion carries the subtle message that when it comes to using DDT to fight Zika, the same hierarchy ought to apply.

But the very same narrative also suggests, not entirely paradoxically, that the United States' past actions cannot be followed by others in the present. Between the war and the ban, according to the DDT narrative, the United States used the pesticide to “eliminate” malaria within its own borders, an achievement that helped set the stage for the global campaign to wipe out the disease.[42] While DDT was an effective tool to combat malaria in the postwar United States, however, it was “only partly” responsible for the “huge blow to Aedes aegypti” dealt by Brazil and other tropical countries, as a New York Times blogger explained.[43] In the spring of 2016, DDT's past successes outside the United States – and in 1950s Brazil in particular – were attributed to “intrusive home inspections” carried out by an “authoritarian government,” with “fumigators sometimes entering houses by force.”[44] Victory over malaria-carrying mosquitoes globally was chalked up to “equal parts authoritarianism, DDT sprays and sanitation.”[45] “It's just a completely different world now,” a prominent entomologist told the press.[46] DDT's success belonged to an antiquated world order and a moment long gone. And while other countries may have needed to combine DDT with authoritarianism and aggression, the United States, according to the narrative, did not.

The DDT narrative has been constructed and recounted precisely because it buttresses a specific US identity, one that highlights the nation's superpower status, its reputation as global leader, and its identity as an exception to global rules. The narrative's omissions make this clear. DDT may have played a crucial role in war, but there was more than combat behind the American public's attitudes toward DDT, both during the war and after its end. After the war, DDT was heavily promoted in a new consumer environment that arose in tandem with an advertising boom, in the context of which it became a valued product for keeping homes and communities pest (and germ) free; it simultaneously found a variety of roles to play in the West's rapidly industrializing agricultural system, from protecting crops to increasing yields of milk and beef.[47] American attitudes toward DDT were also more complicated than the narrative allows, and Carson's role in shaping those attitudes more complicated still. Concerns about DDT's effects on non-target insects, on nature's balance, and on humans through residues in food all preceded Carson, as did worries about the time frame across which DDT's benefits were weighed against its risks. The narrative places the power to right the wrongs of a military-industrial complex in the hands of the populace of a participatory democracy, but this, too, is a deliberately (if unconsciously) selective presentation of the past meant to highlight the effective functioning of checks-and-balances governance. For there were market forces that also made the ban possible but that have no starring role in the narrative.

To take the narrative's beginning, the story of DDT as a signifier of US exceptionalism was shaped early on, when wartime US news reports maintained that because the Swiss had no idea how powerful DDT was, it had to be smuggled out by Americans, the only ones who knew its real power.[48] A few reports even ignored the Swiss connection entirely, presenting DDT as a US discovery. DDT's story was reshaped more subtly and powerfully still in an American context that placed the pesticide's origins not in the late nineteenth century, when an Austrian graduate student synthesized the chemical compound, but three generations later, at the dawn of the American golden age of biomedicine. DDT's power, in this narrative, lies in its discovered utility. An Austrian scientist may have synthesized it, and a Swiss chemist may have uncovered its ability to kill insects, but it was only the Americans who revealed it as a long-unrecognized solution to the greatest complicating factor of all wars: disease. Disconnecting DDT from its nineteenth-century roots became a means of disconnecting twentieth-century American public health and medicine from their own nineteenth-century European roots. DDT, in this story, is a signifier of US modernity – especially scientific modernity – and stands as proof positive of the link between scientific excellence and global might.

Portrayed as a hero during the war, DDT was given a hero's welcome when it returned home to the United States afterwards. This is a critical part of the DDT narrative, which describes a nation so overcome with patriotic faith in science and technocracy that it embraced DDT's application in nearly every aspect of life. This section of the narrative reflects the historiography on DDT, which depicts postwar housewives dousing their homes with DDT bug bombs, city officials faithfully spraying suburban streets, and children “frolicking” in DDT mist, all without question.[49] The same body of literature describes those who expressed worries about DDT or spoke out against it as few in number, dismissed as “hysterical,” and well outside “expert” spheres.[50] Such histories reflect the sources on which they are based: scientific and government reports produced for the war effort and archives of powerful institutions, such as the Rockefeller Foundation, with an express interest in maintaining DDT's reputation for safety and effectiveness because it both prevented disease and, in doing so, powerfully demonstrated Western authority.

Broaden the source base and analytical lens, however, and this history looks different. A wide array of individuals, from FDA scientists to county agents, beekeepers, farmers, and consumers, spent the years during and after the war voicing concerns about DDT's effects on nature and on human health. The story of the pesticide as war hero is not based on such voices – or on the values they represented. When such voices are included in examination of the historical record, they suggest that contemporary illustrations of the postwar DDT-trusting public are misinterpretations.[51] Middle-class housewives doused their kitchens with DDT in postwar ads, newspaper photos, documentary films, and more not necessarily because that was how they already behaved in real life but because it was how they were being instructed to act.[52] The oft-shown National Geographic photograph of a child playing in the spray of a DDT truck emblazoned with the words “DDT … Harmless to Humans” is not evidence that the public didn't fear the insecticide but evidence that they were told there was nothing to fear.[53] When such images are interpreted alongside US Army reports that endorsed DDT's widespread use (albeit in war), they seem to suggest a trusting and embracing public. But the text of that very National Geographic article reported that DDT was harmful to animals and that there were unresolved questions about its safety – messages now lost in misreadings of visual artefacts of the past.

After the war, US health officials deployed DDT against malaria and typhus across the South, and manufacturers advertised (and consumers purchased) DDT to protect themselves from polio, scarlet fever, measles, and more – infections against which DDT proved powerless, and which have therefore been written out of its narrative entirely.[54] But DDT's wartime accomplishment became its postwar promise, which is partly why the DDT narrative overstates its role in eliminating malaria from the United States. Though malaria was fully eradicated six years into DDT's deployment, even the director of the agency that coordinated those efforts said that “the best we can claim … is that we kicked a dying dog.”[55] As Margaret Humphreys shows, credit for malaria elimination is more aptly distributed across postwar prosperity, better housing, improved nutrition, access to drugs, and – above all – policies that relocated the “at-risk population” away from environments in which the mosquito thrived.[56] But in the DDT narrative, the pesticide alone, sprayed on walls by hand and over great swaths of land by plane, eclipses all of these.

The prominence of malaria in the DDT narrative's first act upholds the idea that infectious diseases are problems with singular, easily identified and targeted causes that lend themselves to technological – as opposed to social or political – solutions. It also upholds the basis of public health institution building; as Humphrey notes, the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention grew out of wartime malaria control efforts, giving the agency an interest in promoting continued malaria control efforts after the war.[57] Crediting DDT with malaria's elimination from the United States – even in part – affirms the power of the new wartime institution narratively behind this success even as it discredits social, environmental, and economic means of managing infectious diseases.[58] This act of the narrative also conveys the idea that success is inherent to technology; thus, the public turn against DDT inspired by Silent Spring is the reason behind DDT's downfall – not rapidly spreading insect resistance nor the uneven political will that led the WHO to abandon global malaria eradication before that goal was reached.

The narrative's emphasis on DDT's dual peacetime identities – as public health panacea and consumer commodity – is a meaningful distraction from its role in postwar agriculture. As production of all pesticides ballooned from 100 million to 300 million pounds between 1945 and 1950, DDT production rose from 33 million to more than 100 million pounds.[59] The bulk of this volume went to agricultural use, because DDT seemed the safest and most cost-effective solution to the challenges of postwar agriculture, including labour shortages, increased production costs, and falling commodity prices.[60] By controlling agricultural pests, DDT appeared to increase yields of corn, beef, and milk by as much as 50%, thus reversing or slowing profit losses.[61] But with the US population moving away from rural areas and farms, this use of DDT was far less visible than its deployment against disease-carrying pests and its household use in urban and suburban spaces.[62]

The DDT narrative overlooks the fact that the pesticide's reputational standing in both public health and agriculture was on the decline well before Carson's Silent Spring was published. Newly developed synthetic agricultural chemicals may have been incredibly profitable after the war, but very quickly DDT – off-patent and manufactured by nearly every scale of insecticide maker – was not. Major manufacturer DuPont reported that it lost $0.03 on every pound of DDT it manufactured, a loss that prompted it to cease production in the mid-1950s.[63] DDT's use in agriculture began to fall off at the same time, thanks to spreading insect resistance and growing worries about the pesticide's accumulation in animal fat and milk – and, therefore, in the human diet.[64] Farmers responded by combining DDT with other chemicals or abandoning it altogether, as did public health officials. Health officials' attitudes toward DDT shifted in other ways, too. The WHO's global anti-malaria program, inspired by reports of DDT-driven malaria eradication in North America, made eradication its goal partly because of concerns that spreading insect resistance meant any hope of malaria control would be lost once DDT ceased to work entirely; it had to be used quickly, before it couldn't be used at all.[65] In other words, expert and professional doubts about DDT circulated widely before Carson purportedly turned the public against it.

Carson receives credit for “catalyzing” public environmental concern about DDT,[66] and her book for signalling “the start of the environmental movement.”[67] But her work, like Wakefield's, was a response to pervasive and pre-existing worries. Moreover, as numerous historians highlight, Silent Spring's scope was bigger than birds and DDT; it was a critique of postwar synthetic pesticides and industrial agriculture, and it charged that scientific paradigms were unequipped to detect or quantify the full scope of the new chemicals' risks to humans. As Finis Dunaway, for example, notes, early media coverage of Silent Spring “singled out DDT as the nation's sole pesticide danger,” and the book became well known for its fable of a town in which no birds sang.[68] But it was also a town in which “farmers spoke of much illness among their families” and “doctors had become more and more puzzled.”[69] Man, Carson argued, had created a world in which no one was safe from cancer-causing chemicals and no one was fully capable of measuring or interpreting the risks they posed.

The environmental movement that took on DDT as its seminal cause placed Carson's ideas about environmental causes of cancer at the forefront of its campaigns to have the pesticide banned – another historical reality that the DDT narrative alternately misunderstands and ignores. As activist groups mobilized to secure local bans on DDT in the 1960s, they initially highlighted its harms to wildlife, especially fish and birds. But as their fight against DDT picked up momentum and visibility, they placed the human health risks it posed at the centre of their strategy. Environmentalists collected, repackaged, and publicized evidence that DDT had negative effects on the endocrine systems and livers of animals; was accumulating in human milk; had unknown long-term toxicity in humans; and could be construed as a possible carcinogen, based on animal studies and emerging human epidemiological studies. The epidemiologic findings remain unconfirmed to this day – but it didn't matter.[70] Environmentalists made a deliberate link between DDT and cigarettes and argued that it was unwise to wait decades for definitive proof that the former caused cancer, when doing just that had led to countless preventable deaths from the latter. When the newly formed US Environmental Protection Agency announced that it would cancel DDT's registration (effectively imposing a ban) in 1972, the written decision prominently cited the chemical's potential carcinogenicity – exactly as environmentalists had hoped.[71]

The DDT narrative often presents the moment of the ban as a symbol of the environmental movement's success in overcoming the power of industrial interests and their bureaucratic guardians in order to protect nature. Casting the ban in this way ignores the central role of new health values in turning the popular and political tide against DDT. It also ignores the absence of a commercial interest in or defence of DDT. As Frederick Rowe Davis argues, because DDT was included in thousands of products manufactured by hundreds of companies, banning it “did not place a burden on any one chemical company in the way that banning a proprietary [patented] pesticide would have”; moreover, the ban allowed chemical companies producing proprietary organophosphate pesticides to realize “significant profits” as the agricultural industry switched from DDT to alternatives.[72] What is construed as one of the “greatest successes of the environmental movement,” Davis notes, did little to immediately change overall pesticide use and regulation, and, further, swapped out an acutely nontoxic pesticide for a class of pesticides whose acute toxicity took a greater toll on agricultural workers and wildlife. In other words, an episode commonly read as a seminal victory for the environmental movement could just as well be read as a victory for an industry ready to wash its hands of DDT and move on to more profitable products. “If history teaches us anything,” concludes Davis, “it is to be wary of simple stories.”[73]

DDT's simple story, in both popular and academic texts, is a story of American scientific and cultural modernity, a modernity defined in each new act in the drama by a break from a changing but consistently “archaic and stable past.”[74] The currently prevailing DDT narrative's omissions and inclusions reify Western (and particularly US) power in the postwar period. They place scientific and technological accomplishment at the roots of that power, and they uphold the power and the top-down, technologically determined approach of postwar public health institutions. In emphasizing the power of social movements to remake society for the better, the narrative also supports the self-correcting justness of democratic governance. Lastly, the DDT narrative is a story about how, to borrow Michelle Murphy's articulation, exposures matter, or are made to matter – that is, for reasons that have more to do with power, politics, and social relations than with scientific evidence, some exposures become visible and actionable while others remain hidden or dismissed.[75] How DDT matters as an exposure in its own narrative perhaps signals the narrative's most meaningful departure from the moral of the vaccine narrative.

Narrative Intersection

Narratives, as noted in the introduction to this essay, are not fixed; a narrative's very form changes from one moment to the next, as does its context, its audience, the interests of its authors, its understood meaning, and more. In recent Zika discourse, health experts offered a revised explanation for DDT's downfall. This explanation dates to a set of conversations that took place in the 1990s, about the possibility of bringing back DDT in places where malaria rates were climbing alarmingly. These discussions culminated in a 2006 policy change at the WHO, which endorsed DDT for limited indoor use against malaria in countries with great need. News reports on DDT's place in Zika control acknowledged that the pesticide is still used for malaria control in a number of countries in Africa – and that this is because there is a “responsible” way to use it. The fatal error in past DDT use, as then CDC director Tom Frieden put it, occurred in the agricultural sector, where DDT was applied in misguided and reckless ways – the opposite of the targeted way in which it is applied to save lives.[76] In this third act of the narrative, current experts position themselves as more enlightened than past ones. Their expertise stems in part from learning from past mistakes, and with this wisdom they determine the appropriate limits to govern use of powerful technologies. It is noteworthy that the blame for the damage once wrought by DDT now rests with the agricultural industry: this, specifically, is an explanation for our times, when it has become culturally acceptable (and even fashionable) to blame the excesses and perversions of industrial agriculture for health challenges ranging from obesity to respiratory disease.

But health experts did not endorse DDT for Zika control in 2016. Two of their stated reasons stood out – and stood in (unintended) opposition to public health messaging about vaccines. First, DDT's success belonged, as noted above, to a different world order, and to a bygone relationship between scientific authorities and the public. As two Johns Hopkins University scientists put it, “knocking on any door in the city with the world's safest insecticide and saying, ‘Hello, I'm from the government and I want to spray your home with this chemical. Trust me,’” is “just unthinkable now.”[77] That trust, in short, no longer exists either within nations or between them. Yet this scenario is closely akin to what US health officials ask – or require – through policies that mandate vaccinations for children or promote them abroad. The success of both vaccination and DDT-based disease prevention rely on human populations acting in concert and in deference to scientific authority. The DDT narrative highlights the limits of this approach even as the vaccine narrative demands that it not be questioned. In short, this explanation of DDT's unsuitability points up one way in which the vaccine and DDT narratives intersected at cross-purposes in 2016.

The second reason DDT was not the responsible solution to Zika's spread had to do with the risks it posed – not to wildlife, but to humans. The effects of acute, high-dose DDT exposure are well documented: vomiting, tremors, numbness, and liver damage. But they set in only after such incredibly high doses that they aren't considered an attendant risk of the pesticide's public health deployment. Instead, recent news reports (and historical work), cite the range of long-term health problems potentially associated with DDT exposure: Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, diabetes, developmental delay in children, infertility, breast cancer, and cancer in general. The depth of the evidentiary base supporting these associations varies widely, but that's not why they're cited. They're cited because DDT exposure matters, and to ensure that it continues to matter. Here, again, the DDT and vaccine narratives clash.

Because it persists and bioaccumulates, DDT is the exposure that can't be eliminated. It is an exposure first assumed decades ago in efforts to improve public health, but where DDT's target disease threats are now gone, the pesticide remains – in the environment, wildlife, and human bodies. The DDT narrative does not assure us that these body burdens are safe. Instead, it offers a reminder that additional exposure is too risky to bear. The vaccine narrative, meanwhile, ignores exposure, despite the fact that the social movement that features in the narrative cites exposure as a central concern. The so-called anti-vaccine movement makes the very arguments that the anti-DDT movement did decades ago: that lack of short-term harm is not proof of long-term safety, that there are scientific questions about exposure that scientists do not ask because they are not equipped to answer them, and that exposures matter when their long-term consequences remain uncertain. This part of vaccination history is excised from the vaccine narrative because it enables the narrative to do the work it was constructed to do – deliver the message that exposure does not matter, even as other public health narratives insist that it does.

The exposures in the two public health narratives considered here – MMR in one narrative, DDT in the other – are assumed against specific risks: measles, mumps, and rubella, in the first case, and insect-borne infections such as malaria, dengue, and (possibly) Zika in the second. All of these risks are far outweighed in the West by the risk of many forms of cancer, one of the very hazards potentially associated with DDT, and autism, one of the risks that some vaccine sceptics worry is associated with vaccines. The DDT narrative supports the contention that vaccines are worth worrying about, precisely because cancer looms bigger than Zika and autism looms bigger than measles. Vaccine defenders argue that developed nations are free of measles only because of successful deployment of the vaccine, but to vaccine critics, such arguments involve a value judgement regarding risk that they do not share. As vaccine critic Jenny McCarthy once put it, “If you ask a parent of an autistic child if they want the measles or the autism, we will stand in line for the … measles.”[78] The vaccine, in this view, represents a certain exposure that carries with it a trade-off among uncertain disease risks, one (measles) perceived as preferable to the other (autism) in a specific twenty-first-century context.

McCarthy, once widely quoted and later vilified for her vaccine views, is largely absent from the 2016 vaccine narrative considered in this essay. In her place stands Wakefield, whose followers believe that there are hazards associated with listening uncritically to scientific experts, that experts do not always have the interests of the public in mind, and that it is the right and responsibility of citizens in a democracy to point out the exposures that matter and demand protection from them. These are the lessons of the second act of the DDT narrative, which affirms the importance of listening to scientific figures who push back against establishment norms – like Rachel Carson – and affirms their power to lead social movements. The DDT narrative is one of many postwar scientific narratives about the fallibility of science, which in Harry Collins' view led to the rise of “default expertise” evident in the vaccine narrative.[79] There are numerous, critically important distinctions between Wakefield and Carson, of course, not least of which is the fact that Wakefield was found guilty of scientific misconduct and stripped of his expert credentials. But both sustained remarkably parallel attacks in their own time: that they were purveyors of “junk” science, embraced visions clouded by their values, elevated emotion over reason, and endangered public welfare by spreading misinformation about technologies critical to human survival. Both despite and for these reasons, each one plays a pivotal role in a public health narrative that tells citizens who they are and how, as biocitizens, they should behave.[80]

The narratives agree, however, that health citizens must subordinate individual privilege to the pursuit of public health. As an expert in public health law told the Wall Street Journal, opposition to DDT and related pesticides comes “largely from privileged northerners who aren't dying of mosquito-borne illnesses.”[81] This position posits DDT doubts as self-centred – akin to how vaccine avoiders have been cast in the vaccine narrative. Such individuals “are just incredibly selfish,” a paediatric disease expert said during California's 2015 measles outbreak.[82] Media reports have also cast “anti-vaccine” parents as privileged members of their own society, tying selfishness to material wealth in the same way the DDT narrative does. The ability to accept or reject risks of different types is a privilege that operates at different scales in both narratives – but in both cases it is an obstacle to the pursuit of public health, the achievement of which is predicated on the exchange of individual rights or privileges for the collective good.

The two narratives instruct health citizens to make different uses of the past. In the vaccine narrative, the past is a reminder of the risks of preventable diseases, a time when infections such as smallpox, polio, diphtheria, and measles sickened children and sometimes killed them, a time before technology gave humanity the means to keep such threats at bay. In the DDT narrative, the past is a cautionary tale against the misuse of technologies in the present; past haste to use technology, heedless of long-term consequences, is a warning against thinking in too limited a way about risks and benefits today. These are, in sum, stories with opposing morals on multiple levels, circulating in the same moment and speaking to the same ostensible end goal of improved public health. Or, at least, they are as I have laid them out here. Historians, writes Patrick Finney, “have always been involved in fabricating subjective ideological constructs, interested representations rather than neutral reconstructions of the past.”[83] And in considering these narratives, I too have created a new and inherently subjective one through the process of curating the stories, and histories, referenced here.

In doing so, I have overlooked points of commonality, overlap, intersection, and contradiction. Both DDT and vaccines have been employed and envisioned as tools of infectious disease control, if not elimination; both have achieved remarkable success in that respect; and both have been used with force on disempowered and subaltern populations.[84] Both narratives concern environmental values – regarding what is natural and the ramifications of human interaction with nature.[85] Vaccines and DDT control very different types of diseases, one a collection of largely “childhood” infections, the other an ever-evolving list of emerging insect-borne threats. Vaccines are now used as a matter of routine; DDT is now invoked (in places of privilege) only as an emergency measure. One affects the health of living children; the other (with respect to Zika) the unborn. The vaccine narrative ignores global health; the DDT narrative places it in service of national identity. Issues of race, class, and gender shape both narratives in ways I have not even mentioned in passing here. But it was not my aim to suggest that these and only these narratives are uniquely comparable, or to be exhaustive in comparing the two.

I have created this narrative shape to serve a particular agenda. History's main contribution to civil society, I believe, is its potential not just to tell stories but to tell them differently than they have been told before. The omissions in the DDT and vaccine narratives highlighted here signal, to me, the great need for historians to continue to do what we do best: closely examine sources, bring new evidence to light, and tell the stories that have not yet been told, particularly when it comes to some of the most deeply embedded stories circulating in the history and practice of medicine and public health. In the history of medicine, as in any subfield, we have the stories we reach for as shorthand for what happened when and why. The stories we reach for so easily, the ones we assume we all know, are exactly the ones most worthy of further exploration.

A generation ago, Cronon invited environmental historians to tell more stories about stories. Telling stories about our stories about the past has much potential to shed light on contemporary scientific debates and stalemates, by enabling us to see how our narratives uphold our competing senses of ourselves, and our great public health and medical challenges, in the present. Because our stories are our histories and prophecies both, as Cronon put it, telling stories about our stories can help us contribute to broader conversations about future directions for medical and public health practice and policy – something historians, though sometimes loath, are uniquely well positioned to do.

Acknowledgments

Thanks to the Center for Science, Technology, Medicine and Society MEDS group at the University of California, Berkeley, for invaluable feedback on this essay. An early version of this essay was presented as the AMS-Paterson Lecture at the 2016 CSHM-SCHM Conference, and I am grateful for attendees' insightful remarks and critical commentary. Research for this essay was supported in part by a 2015–2016 Cain Fellowship from the Chemical Heritage Foundation.

Notes

Public health is a project of the state, and states have traditionally relied on mainstream news outlets to reach the public. My interest in considering how narrative influences the pursuit of public health goals, therefore, limited my source base to mainstream media sources. I acknowledge that different narratives about DDT and vaccines circulate on blogs, Facebook groups, websites serving specific interests or patient groups, and elsewhere, but I do not consider these narratives part of the state's pursuit of public health.

On narrative theory see, from a vast literature, Robert Scholes, James Phelan, and Robert Kellogg, The Nature of Narrative (New York: Oxford University Press, 2006), 4.

Charles L. Briggs and Daniel C. Hallin, Making Health Public: How News Coverage Is Remaking Media, Medicine, and Contemporary Life (New York: Routledge, 2016).

Jouni-Matti Kuukkanen, “The Missing Narrativist Turn in the Historiography of Science,” History and Theory 51 (2012): 340–63.

See, e.g., David Carr, Time, Narrative and History: An Essay in the Philosophy of History (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1986); Hayden White, The Content of the Form: Narrative Discourse and Historical Representation (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1987).

William Cronon, “A Place for Stories: Nature, History, and Narrative,” Journal of American History 78 (1992): 1347–76, 1349.

Cronon, “A Place for Stories,” 1350.

Arthur Allen, Vaccine: The Controversial Story of Medicine's Greatest Lifesaver (New York: W.W. Norton, 2007); James K. Colgrove, State of Immunity: The Politics of Vaccination in Twentieth-Century America (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2006); Donald A. Henderson, Smallpox: The Death of a Disease (New York: Prometheus, 2009); Paul A. Offit, Vaccinated: One Man's Quest to Defeat the World's Deadliest Diseases (Washington, DC: Smithsonian Books, 2007).

Andrew J. Wakefield et al., “Ileal-Lymphoid-Nodular Hyperplasia, Non-specific Colitis, and Pervasive Developmental Disorder in Children,” The Lancet 351 (1998): 637–41.

See, e.g., Seth Mnookin, The Panic Virus: A True Story of Medicine, Science, and Fear (New York: Simon & Schuster, 2012).

Steven Salzberg, “Anti-vaccine Movement Causes Worst Measles Epidemic in 20 Years,” Forbes, 1 February 2015. (All online news sources were accessed through the Access World News database.) On the outbreak, see Jennifer Zipprich, “Measles Outbreak – California, December 2014–February 2015,” Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 64, no. 6 (2015): 153–54.

Lucy Westcott, “Toddler Dies from Measles in Berlin's Worst Outbreak in a Decade,” Newsweek, 14 February 2015.

Laura Parker, “The Anti-Vaccine Generation: How Movement against Shots Got Its Start,” National Geographic, 6 February 2015.

Rong-Gong Lin II and Sandra Poindexter, “California Schools' Risks Rise as Vaccinations Drop,” Los Angeles Times, 29 March 2009.

Clyde Haberman, “A Discredited Vaccine Study's Continuing Impact on Public Health,” New York Times, 1 February 2015.

Laura June, “Why Is an Anti-Vaccine Documentary by a Proven Quack Being Taken Seriously?” New York Magazine, 22 March 2016; Maggie Mallon, “Tribeca Film Festival Will Screen Highly Questionable Anti-Vaccine Film,” Glamour, 25 March 2016; Jacqueline Burt Cote, “New Anti-Vax Documentary Could Put Kids' Lives in Danger,” The Stir, 24 March 2016.

Daniel Kreps, “Robert De Niro, Tribeca Film Fest Pull Anti-Vaxxer Documentary,” Rolling Stone, 27 March 2016.

June, “Why Is an Anti-Vaccine Documentary.”

Emily Willingham, “Robert De Niro Turns Scientist, Tribeca Pulls Wakefield Video,” Forbes, 26 March 2016.

Mary Elizabeth Williams, “Anti-Vaxxer's Tribeca Triumph,” Salon, 23 March 2016.

Elena Conis, Vaccine Nation: America's Changing Relationship with Immunization (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2015), 116–29.

For a detailed analysis of Wakefield's work, see Mark A. Largent, Vaccine: The Debate in Modern America (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2012), 94–135.

Conis, Vaccine Nation, 143–44.

Gerald E. Markowitz and David Rosner, Deceit and Denial: The Deadly Politics of Industrial Pollution (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2002); Susan E. Bell, DES Daughters: Embodied Knowledge and the Transformation of Women's Health Politics (Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 2009).

Conis, Vaccine Nation, 150–53.

Elena Conis, “‘Do We Really Need Hepatitis B on the Second Day of Life?’ Vaccination Mandates and Shifting Representations of Hepatitis B,” Journal of Medical Humanities 32 (2011): 155–66; Robert Johnston, “Contemporary Anti-Vaccination Movements in Historical Perspective,” in Robert Johnston, ed., The Politics of Healing: Histories of Alternative Medicine in Twentieth-Century North America (New York: Routledge, 2004), 259–86.

Conis, Vaccine Nation, 179–202.

Largent, Vaccine, 157–64.

SB-277, c. 35 (2015).

On DDT's history, see Thomas Dunlap, DDT: Scientists, Citizens, and Public Policy (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1981); David Kinkela, DDT and the American Century: Global Health, Environmental Politics, and the Pesticide That Changed the World (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2011).

Stockholm Convention on Persistent Organic Pollutants, adopted 22 May 2001, entered into force 17 May 2004; see http://chm.pops.int/.

See, e.g., Henry I. Miller, “Is There a Place for DDT?” New York Times, 7 August 2003, A23.

Walecia Konrad, “Sleeping with the Enemy (Bed Bugs),” New York Times, 11 July 2009, B6.

Owen Dyer, “Zika Virus Spreads across Americas as Concerns Mount over Birth Defects,” BMJ 351 (2015): h6983; World Health Organization [WHO], Zika Situation Report: Neurological Syndrome and Congenital Anomalies (Geneva: WHO, 2016).

Udani Samarasekera and Marcia Triunfol, “Concern over Zika Virus Grips the World,” Lancet 387 (2016): 521–24.

Andrew Pollack, “New Weapon to Fight Zika: The Mosquito,” New York Times, 30 January 2016, https://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/31/business/new-weapon-to-fight-zika-the-mosquito.html; Betsy McKay, Reed Johnson, and Rogerio Jelmayer, “Fighting the ‘Cockroach of Mosquitoes,’” Wall Street Journal, 12 February 2016, https://www.wsj.com/articles/fighting-the-cockroach-of-mosquitoes-1455238636.

Samarasekera and Triunfol, “Concern over Zika”; WHO, Zika Situation Report.

Pollack, “New Weapon to Fight Zika.”

Justin Worland, “Why Bringing Back DDT to Fight Zika Mosquitoes Could Backfire,” Time, 3 February 2016, http://time.com/4205214/zika-virus-ddt-mosquitoes/.

Glenn Garvin, “The Deadliest Insect in Human History: From Yellow Fever to Dengue to Zika, One Mosquito Species Has Been a Ruthless Killer,” Los Angeles Times, 14 February 2016, A3.

Robyn Dixon, “Biological Weapons Target Zika,” Los Angeles Times, 8 February 2016, A6; Pollack, “New Weapon to Fight Zika.”

Worland, “Why Bringing Back DDT.”

Andrew Revkin, “As WHO Declares Zika a Global Health Emergency, a Look at the World's Failed Mosquito Policies,” New York Times, 1 February 2016, https://dotearth.blogs.nytimes.com/2016/02/01/as-w-h-o-weighs-zika-as-emergency-a-look-at-the-worlds-failed-mosquito-policies/.

Andrew Jacobs, “Brazil Pushes Public to Do Its Part,” New York Times, 14 February 2016, https://www.nytimes.com/2016/02/15/world/americas/brazil-pushes-public-to-do-its-part-in-fighting-zika-spread.html; Alexandra Zavis, “Brazil Has Battled the Zika Mosquito Before,” Los Angeles Times, 14 August 2016, A1.

Sabrina Tavernise, “Why Can't We Get Rid of Mosquitoes Entirely?” New York Times, 14 April 2016, https://www.nytimes.com/2016/04/14/insider/why-cant-we-get-rid-of-mosquitoes-entirely.html.

Zavis, “Brazil Has Battled.”

On DDT's place among consumer goods for disease prevention, see David Oshinsky, Polio: An American Story (New York: Oxford University Press, 2006), 3; Nancy Tomes, The Gospel of Germs: Men, Women, and the Microbe in American Life (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1999), 246. On agriculture, see J.L. Anderson, Industrializing the Corn Belt: Agriculture, Technology, and the Environment (Dekalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 2009).

“DDT Outlook,” Soap and Sanitary Chemicals 20 (1944): 127–29, 147.

Finis Dunaway, Seeing Green: The Use and Abuse of American Environmental Images (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2015), 24; James Whorton, Before Silent Spring: Pesticides and Public Health in Pre-DDT America (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974).

Edmund Russell, War and Nature: Fighting Humans and Insects with Chemicals from World War I to Silent Spring (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2001); Whorton, Before Silent Spring.

Elena Conis, “DDT Disbelievers: Health and the New Economic Poisons in Georgia after World War II,” Southern Spaces, 28 October 2016.

US Department of Agriculture and US Public Health Service, “DDT … For Control of Household Pests” (Washington, DC: Federal Security Agency, 1947); Dawn Biehler, Pests in the City: Flies, Bedbugs, Cockroaches, and Rats (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 2013), 91.

F. Barrows Colton, “Your New World of Tomorrow,” National Geographic Magazine, October 1945, 385–410.

See, e.g., “Protect your children against disease-carrying insects!” (print ad, 1947), Chemical Heritage Foundation, Phil Allegretti Pesticide Collection, Object ID 2014.010.114.

Margaret Humphreys, Malaria: Poverty, Race, and Public Health in the United States (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001), 151.

Humphreys, Malaria, 110–12, 149–50.

Humphreys, Malaria, 140–41.

Frank M. Snowden, The Conquest of Malaria: Italy, 1900–1962 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2006), 201.

Christopher J. Bosso, Pesticides and Politics: The Life Cycle of a Public Issue (Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1987), 63; National Archives at Atlanta [NARA], RG 442 (CDC), Historical Files, 66A0163, Box 1, Folder: Economic Poisons, Trend Report: Economic Poisons, 1955.

Anderson, Industrializing the Corn Belt, 23, 31, 64; Bosso, Pesticides and Politics.

Anderson, Industrializing the Corn Belt, 17; “Use of DDT around Dairies in Florida Proves Success,” Valley Morning Star (Harlingen, Texas), 9 December 1945, 19; “DDT Legislation before Congress,” New York Times, 4 December 1945, 46.

Bosso, Pesticides and Politics, 64; Biehler, Pests in the City.

David A. Hounshell and John Kenly Smith, Science and Corporate Strategy: Du Pont R & D, 1902–1980 (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), 453; Benjamin Ross and Steven Amter, The Polluters: The Making of Our Chemically Altered Environment (New York: Oxford University Press, 2010), 57.

Anderson, Industrializing the Corn Belt, 19; Frederick Rowe Davis, Banned: A History of Pesticides and the Science of Toxicology (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2014), 116–52.

National Communicable Disease Center Malaria Eradication Program, “DDT in Malaria Control and Eradication,” 1969, WHO Archives, Folder V2 / 372 / 7 Relations with the Commission on Pesticides of the U.S. Department of Health Education and Welfare.

Nancy Langston, Toxic Bodies: Hormone Disruptors and the Legacy of DES (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2010), 83, 85.

John Opie, Nature's Nation: An Environmental History of the United States (Fort Worth: Harcourt Brace College Publishers, 1998), 413.

Dunaway, Seeing Green, 31.

Rachel Carson, Silent Spring: Fortieth Anniversary Edition (New York: Houghton Mifflin, 2002), 2.

See, e.g., Brenda Eskenazi et al., “The Pine River Statement: Human Health Consequences of DDT Use,” Environmental Health Perspectives 117 (2009): 1359–67; Lino Del Pup et al., “Endocrine Disruptors and Female Cancer,” Oncology Reports 34 (2015): 3–11; Anne-Mary Lewis-Mikhael et al., “Organochlorine Pesticides and Prostate Cancer: Is There an Association? A Meta-analysis of Epidemiological Evidence,” Cancer Causes and Control 26 (2015): 1375–92.

Elena Conis, “Debating the Health Effects of DDT: Thomas Jukes, Charles Wurster, and the Fate of an Environmental Pollutant,” Public Health Reports 125 (2010): 337–42.

Davis, Banned, 219.

Davis, Banned, 188.

Bruno Latour, We Have Never Been Modern (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1993), 10.

Michelle Murphy, Sick Building Syndrome and the Problem of Uncertainty: Environmental Politics, Technoscience, and Women Workers (Durham: Duke University Press, 2006), 18. See also Gregg Mitman, Michelle Murphy, and Christopher Sellers, eds., Landscapes of Exposure: Knowledge and Illness in Modern Environments (Osiris [2nd ser.] 19; Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004); Linda Nash, Inescapable Ecologies: A History of Environment, Disease, and Knowledge (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2006).

Errol Barnett, “New Cases of Zika Virus in China, Australia,” CNN Newsroom, 11 February 2016, http://edition.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/1602/11/cnr.20.html.

David Bishai and Clive Shiff, “Zika: A Wake-Up Call,” Baltimore Sun, 23 February 2016, 13A.

Paul A. Offit, Deadly Choices: How the Anti-Vaccine Movement Threatens Us All (New York: Basic Books, 2011), 152.

Harry Collins, Are We All Scientific Experts Now? (Malden: Polity Press, 2014).

Dorothy Porter, Health, Civilization, and the State: A History of Public Health from Ancient to Modern Times (London: Routledge, 1999), 57; Adriana Petryna, Life Exposed: Biological Citizens after Chernobyl (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2002).

McKay et al., “Fighting the ‘Cockroach of Mosquitoes.’

Yahoo Health, “People Who Skip Vaccinations ‘Incredibly Selfish’ Experts Say,” Yahoo News, 23 January 2015.

Patrick Finney, “International History, Theory and the Origins of World War II,” in Geoffrey Roberts, ed., The History and Narrative Reader (New York: Routledge, 2001), 400.

Conis, “DDT Disbelievers.”

See, e.g., Conis, Vaccine Nation, 131–58.